Hi, this is the first lecture in MIT's
course 18.06 linear algebra.
And I'm Gilbert Strang.
Um the text for the course is uh this
book
uh introduction to linear algebra.
And uh the course web page, which has
got a lot of
exercises from the past, uh MATLAB
codes,
uh the syllabus for the course is
web.mit.edu/18.06.
And this is the first lecture, lecture
one.
So uh and later we'll say
where which we'll give the web address
for viewing these uh video tapes.
Okay, so what's in the first lecture? Um
This is my plan.
Uh the fundamental problem of linear
algebra,
which is to solve a system of linear
equations.
So let's start with the case when we
have some number of equations, say n
equations and n unknowns.
So an equal number of equations and
unknowns. That's the normal nice case.
And what I want to do
is with examples, of course,
to describe
first
uh what I call the row picture.
That's the picture of one equation at a
time. It's the picture you've seen
before in two by two equations where
lines meet. So in a minute you'll see
lines meeting.
The second picture, I'll I'll I put a
star beside that cuz that's such an
important one and maybe new to you is
the picture a column at a time.
And those are the rows and columns of a
matrix. So the third, the algebra way to
look at the problem is the matrix form
in using a matrix that I'll call A.
Okay, so can I
do an example? The whole semester will
be
uh examples and then
see what's going on with the with the
example. So
take an example.
Two equations, two unknowns.
So let me take
2x
- y = 0, let's say, and - x + say 2y =
3.
Okay.
Uh let me I can even say right away
what's the matrix
that that is what's the coefficient
matrix? The matrix that involves these
numbers. A matrix is just a
rectangular array of numbers. Here the
here it's two rows and two columns. So
two and minus one in the first row,
minus one and two in the second row.
That's the matrix.
And the right hand the uh unknown,
well, we've got two unknowns. So we've
got a vector x with two components x and
y and we've got two right hand sides
that go into a vector 0 3.
I couldn't resist writing the matrix
form uh right of even before the before
the pictures. So I always will think of
this as the matrix A,
the matrix of coefficients. Then there's
a vector of unknowns. Here we've only
got two unknowns. Later we'll have any
number of unknowns. And that vector of
unknowns, well, I'll often I'll make
that x extra extra bold. Uh
and the right hand side is also a vector
that I'll always call B.
So linear equations are Ax = B and the
idea now is to solve this particular
example and then step back to see the
bigger picture.
Okay, what's the picture for this
example? The row picture.
Okay, so here comes the row picture.
So that means I take one row at a time
and I'm drawing here the
xy plane
and I'm going to
put
plot all the points that satisfy that
first equation.
So I'm looking at all the points that
satisfy 2x - y = 0. I I'm often it's
often good to start with which point on
the
horizontal line. On this horizontal
line, y is zero.
The x-axis has y is zero and that in
this case actually then x is zero. So
the point,
the origin, the point with coordinates 0
is on the line. It solves that equation.
Okay,
uh tell me an Well, I guess I have to
tell you
uh another point that solves this
uh same equation. Let me suppose x is
one.
So I'll take x to be one,
then y should be two, right?
So there's
the point 1 2
that also solves this equation. And I
could put in more points.
But but uh let me put in all the points
at once because they all lie
on a straight line. This is a linear
equation and that word linear got the
letters for line in it.
That's the equation. That's this is the
line that of that of solutions to 2x - y
= 0, my first row, first equation.
So typically maybe x equal a half, y
equal one
will work and it sure enough it does.
Okay.
That's the first one. Now the second one
is not going to go through the origin.
It's always important do we go through
the origin or not?
In this case, yes, because there's a
zero over there. In this case, we don't
go through the origin because
if x and y are zero, we don't get three.
So
let me again say, suppose y is zero,
what x do we actually get? If y is zero,
then I get
x is
minus three.
So if y is zero, I go along minus three.
So there's one point on this second
line.
Now let me say, well, suppose x is minus
one.
Just to take another x. If x is minus
one, then this is a one
and I think y should be a one.
Cuz if x is minus one, then I think y
should be a one and we'll get that
point.
Is that right? If x is minus one, that's
a one. If y is a one, that's a two and
the one and the two make three and that
point's on the equation. Okay, now I
should just draw the line, right?
Connecting those two points at that will
give me the whole line. And if I've done
this
reasonably well, I think it's going to
happen to go through Well, not happen.
It was arranged to go through that
point. So I think that the second line
is this one and this is the
all-important point that lies on both
lines.
Shall we just check that that point,
which which is the point x equal one and
y was two, right? That's the point there
and that I believe solves both
equations.
Let's just check this. If x is one, I
have a minus one
plus four equals three.
Okay.
Apologies for drawing this picture that
you've seen
before.
But
uh this seeing the row picture
first of all for n equal two, two
equations and two unknowns, it's the
right place to start.
Okay, so we've got the solution, the
point that lies on both lines. Now can I
come to the column picture?
Pay attention. This is the key point.
So the column picture.
I'm now going to look at the columns of
the matrix. I'm going to look at this
part and this part. I'm going to say
that the the x part is really So
so it is really x times
You see I'm putting the two I'm I'm I'm
kind of getting the two equations at
once.
That part and then I have a y and and in
the first equation it's multiplying a
minus one and in the second equation a
two. And on the right hand side, zero
and three.
You see the columns of the matrix? The
columns of A are here and the right hand
side B is there.
And now what is the equation asking for?
It's asking us to find somehow to to
combine that vector and this one in the
right amounts to get that one.
It's asking us to find the right linear
combination. This is called a linear
combination.
And it's the most fundamental operation
in the whole course.
It's a linear combination of the
columns.
That's what we're seeing on the left
side.
Again,
I don't want to write down a big
definition. You can see what it is.
There's column one, there's column two.
I multiply by some numbers
and I add.
That's a combination, a linear
combination, and I want to make those
numbers the right numbers to produce 0
3.
Okay.
Now, I want to draw a picture that
represents what this This is algebra.
What's the geometry? What's the picture
that goes with it? Okay. So, again,
these vectors have two components, so I
better
draw a picture like that. So, can I put
down these columns? I'll draw these
columns as they are, and then I'll
do do a combination of them. So, the
first column is over two and down one,
right?
So, there's the first column.
The first column. Column one.
It's the vector 2 - 1.
The second column
is Let's see. I go over minus one is the
first component and up two. It's here.
There's column two.
So, this again,
you see what its components are. Its
components are minus one, two.
Good. That's this guy. Now, what is what
Now, I have to take a combination.
What combination shall I take?
Why not the right combination? What the
hell? Okay. So, what the combination I'm
going to take
is the right one to produce 0 3, and
then and then we'll see it happen in the
picture. So, the right combination is to
take X is one of those
and two of these.
It's because we already know that that's
the right X and Y, so why not take the
correct combination here and see it
happen. Okay. So, how do I picture this
this linear combination? So, I start
with this vector that's already here.
So, that's one of column one. That's one
times column one. Right there.
And now I want to add on, so I'm going
to hook the next vector on
to the
front of the arrow. We'll start the next
vector and it'll go this way. So, let's
see. Can I do it right? If
I add it on one of these vectors, it
would go left one and up two. So, it
probably get us to there. Maybe I'll do
dotted line for that. Okay. That's one
of column two
tucked on to the end, but I wanted to
tuck on two of column two. So, that the
second one will go up left one and up
two also. It'll probably end there. And
there's another one. So, so what I've
put in here is two of column two
added on.
And where did I end up?
What are the coordinates of this
result?
What do I get when I take one of this
plus two of that?
I do get that, of course.
There it is. There it is. X is zero, Y
is three. That's B. That's the That's
the answer we wanted. And how do I do
it? You see I do it just like the first
component, I have a two and a and a
minus two. That produces a zero. And
then the second component, I have a
minus one and a four. They combine to
give the three.
But look at this picture.
So, here's our key picture. I I combine
this column and this column to get Maybe
I better
to get this guy. That was the B. That's
the 0 3.
Okay.
So,
that idea of linear combinations is
crucial and and also
do we want to think about this question?
Sure, why not?
What are all the combinations? If I took
Can I go back to X's and Y's?
This is a
This is a question for really
it's
it's going to come up over and over, but
why don't we see it once now?
If I took all the X's and all the Y's,
all the combinations,
what would be all the results?
And actually, the result would be that I
could get any right-hand side at all.
The combinations of this and this would
fill the whole plane.
You can tuck that
away. We'll
explore it further.
But this idea of what linear combination
gives B
and what do all the linear combinations
give? What are all the possible
achievable right-hand sides B? That's
going to be basic. Okay. Can I move to
three equations and three unknowns? Cuz
it's easy to
picture the two by two case. Let me do a
three by three example.
Okay. I'll sort of start at the same
way. Say maybe 2X - Y and maybe I'll
take no no Z's is a zero. And maybe a
minus X and a 2Y
and maybe a minus Z is a
Oh, let me make that a minus one. And
just for variety, let me take
minus 3Z
minus 3Y's. I should keep the Y's in
that line. And 4Z's is say four.
Okay.
That's three equations.
I'm in three dimensions, XYZ.
And
I don't have a solution
yet.
So, I want to understand the equations
and then solve them.
Okay. So, how do I How do you understand
them? The row picture is one way. The
column picture is another very important
way. Just Let's remember the matrix form
here, cuz that's easy. The matrix form,
what's our matrix A?
Our matrix A is this right-hand side,
the two and the minus one and the zero
from the first row. The minus one and
the two and the minus one from the
second row. The zero, the minus three,
and the four
from the third row.
So, it's a three by three matrix.
Three equations, three unknowns. And
what's our right-hand side? Of course,
it's
the vector 0 - 1 4.
Okay. So, that's the way Well,
that's the shorthand to write out the
three equations.
But it's the picture that I'm looking
for today. Okay. So, the row picture.
All right. So,
I'm in three dimensions, X Y and Z.
And I want to take those equations one
at a time
and ask and make a picture of all the
points that satisfy Let's take equation
number two.
If I make a picture of all the points
that satisfy, all the XYZ points
that solve this equation.
Well, first of all, the origin is not
one of them. XYZ being 0 0 0 would not
solve that equation. So, what what are
some points that do solve the equation?
Let's see. Maybe if X is one,
Y and Z could be zero. That would work,
right? So, there's one point.
I'm looking at this second equation here
just
to start with. Let's see. Also, I guess
if Z Z could be one, X and Y could be
zero. So, that would just go straight up
that axis.
And probably I want a third point here.
Let me take X to be
zero.
Let's say X to be zero, Z to be zero,
then Y would be minus a half, right?
So, there's a third point somewhere Oh,
my. Okay.
Let's see.
I want to put in all the points that
satisfy that equation. Do you know what
that bunch of points will be?
It's a plane. If we have a linear
equation, then fortunately, the graph of
the thing, the the plot of all the
points that solve it are a plane.
So, I and three these three points
determine a plane, but
your lecturer is not Rembrandt, and this
the art is going to be
the weak point here. So, I'm just going
to draw a plane, right? There's a plane
somewhere. That's my plane. That draw
that that that plane is all the points
that solves this guy.
Then,
what about
this one?
2x - y + 0 z's. So, z actually can be
anything. Again, it's going to be
another plane.
Each row in a 3 by 3 problem gives us a
plane in three dimensions. So, this one
is going to be some other plane. Maybe
it Maybe I'll try to draw it like this.
And those two planes meet in a
line.
So, if I have two equations,
just the first two equations in in three
dimensions, those give me a line. The
line where those two planes meet. And
now,
the third
guy
is a third plane.
And it goes some
somewhere.
Okay, those three things meet in a
point. Now, I don't know where that
point is, frankly.
Uh but uh linear algebra will find it.
Main point is
that there is that the three planes,
because they're
you know, they're not parallel, they
don't they're not special, they're
they do meet in one point, and that's
the solution. But,
uh maybe you can see that this row
picture is getting a little hard to see.
The row picture was a cinch
uh when we looked at two two lines
meeting. When we look at three planes
meeting, it's not so clear, and
in four dimensions, probably a little
less clear. So,
can I quit on the row picture?
I'll quit on the row picture before I've
successfully found the point where the
three planes meet.
All I really want to to see is that
there
the the row picture consists of three
planes, and
if everything works right, three planes
meet in one point, and that's the
solution. Now,
you can tell I prefer the column
picture.
Okay? So, let me take the column
picture. That's x times
So, there were two x's in the first
equation, minus one x's. I'm just take
and no x's in the third. It's just the
first column of that.
And how many y's are there? There's
minus one in the first equation, two in
the second, and maybe minus three in the
third.
Just the second column of my matrix. And
z
times no z's, minus one z's, and four
z's.
And it's those three columns, right?
That I have to combine to produce
the right-hand side, which is 0 - 1 4.
Okay.
So, what have we got on this left-hand
side?
A linear combination. It's a linear
combination now of three vectors, and
they happen to be Each one is a
three-dimensional vector. So, we want to
We want to know what combination of
those three vectors produces that one.
Shall I try to draw the column picture
then?
So, since these vectors have three
components, so it's some multiple Well,
let me draw in the first column as
before. So, I x is two, and y is minus
one. Maybe Maybe there's the first
column.
Why the second column has maybe a minus
one and a two in the y's and minus three
some somewhere there, possibly.
Column two.
And the third column has no
no 0 - 1 4.
So, how should I draw that? So, nothing
in this is This was the This was the
first component, the second component
was a minus one. Maybe up here.
That's column three. That's
That's the column 0 - 1 and 4. This guy.
So, again, what's my problem? My My What
this equation is asking me to do is to
combine these three vectors
with a right
combination to produce this one.
Well,
you can see what the right combination
is.
Because in this
special problem,
specially chosen by the lecturer, uh
that right-hand side that I'm trying to
get is actually one of these columns.
So, I know how to get that one. So,
what's the solution?
What combination will work?
I just want one of these and none of
these. So, x should be zero, y should be
zero, and z should be one.
The com- That's the combination. None of
that, none of that, one of those is
obviously the right one. So, this column
three is actually the same as b in this
particular problem.
I
I I made it work that way just so we
would get an answer, 0 0 1. So, somehow
that's the point
that where those three planes met, and I
couldn't see it before.
Of course, I won't always be able to see
it
from the column picture, either.
It's
the next lecture, actually,
which is about elimination, which is the
systematic way that everybody
every
every bit of software, too,
uh
a production large-scale software would
solve the the equations. So, the the
lecture that's coming up, if I was to
add that to the
to the syllabus, will be about
how to find x y z in
in all cases.
Can I just
think again, though, about the big
picture?
The big By the big picture, I mean,
let's keep this same matrix on the left,
but imagine that we have a different
right-hand side.
Oh, let me take a different right-hand
side.
Uh so, I'll change that right-hand side
to something that actually is also
pretty special.
Let me change it to Suppose I If I add
those first two columns, that would give
me a one and a one and a minus three.
There's a very special right-hand side.
I I just cooked it up by adding this one
to this one.
Now, what's the solution with this new
right-hand side?
The solution with this new right-hand
side is clear. It took Now, I took one
of these,
one of these, and none of those. So, So,
actually, it just changed around to this
when I took this new right-hand side.
Okay.
So, the in the in the row picture, I
have three different planes.
Three three three new planes meeting now
at this point. In the column picture, I
have the same three columns, but now I'm
combining them to produce this guy. And
it turned out that column one plus
column two, which would be somewhere
there, there is the right column.
One of this and one of this would give
me the the new b.
Okay. So, that's like we squeezed in an
extra example. But, now think about all
b's.
All right-hand sides.
Could I get Can I solve these equations
for every right-hand side?
Uh it Can I say that ask that question?
So, that's the algebra question.
Can I solve Ax = b for every b?
Let me write that down.
Can I solve
Ax = b
for every
right-hand side b?
I mean, is there a solution?
And then,
if there is, elimination will give me a
way to find it. I'm just I really wanted
to ask, is there a solution for every
right-hand side?
So, now, can I put that in different
words?
In this linear combination words. So, in
linear combination words, do the
linear
combinations
of the columns
fill
three-dimensional space?
Every b
means all the b's in three-dimensional
space.
So, I'm Do you see that I'm just asking
the same question in in different words?
Solving a
Ax Oh, that's very important.
A times x, when I multiply a matrix by a
vector,
I get a combination of the columns. Let
me I'll write that
down in a moment.
So, that
Do you see But, in my column picture,
that's really what I'm doing. I'm taking
linear combinations of these three
columns, and I'm trying to find
B.
And actually, the answer for this matrix
will be yes. For this matrix, for this
for this
matrix A, for these columns, the answer
is
yes.
This matrix is this this this matrix
that
that that I chose for an example
is a good matrix, a non-singular matrix,
an invertible matrix. So, those will be
the matrices that we like best.
There could be other
and we will see other matrices where the
answer becomes no.
Oh, actually, you can see when it would
become no.
When could
What What could go wrong? How could it
go wrong that out of these out of three
columns
and all their combinations
when would I not be able to produce some
B off here?
When When could it go wrong?
Do you see that the combinations
Suppo- Let me say when it goes wrong.
If these three columns all lie in the
same plane
then their combinations will lie
in that same plane.
So, then we're in trouble. If the three
columns of my matrix
if those three vectors happen to lie in
the same plane
for example, if column three is just the
sum of column one and column two
I would be in trouble.
That would be a matrix A where the
answer would be no.
Because the combinations
if column three is in the same plane as
column one and two, I don't get anything
new from that. All the combinations are
in the plane, and the only right-hand
sides B that I could get would be the
ones in that plane.
So, I could solve it for some right-hand
sides
when B is in the in the plane, but most
right-hand sides would be out of the
plane and unreachable.
So, that would be a singular case. The
matrix would be not invertible. There
would not be a solution for every B. The
answer would become no for that.
Okay.
Um
I don't know
Should we take just a little shot at
thinking about
nine dimensions?
Imagine that we have
vectors with nine components.
Well,
it's going to be hard to visualize
those.
Uh I don't pretend to do it, but somehow
pretend you do.
Pretend we have if if this was nine
equations in nine unknowns, then we
would have nine columns
and each one would be a vector in
nine-dimensional space, and we would be
looking at their linear combinations.
So, we we'd having the linear
combinations of nine vectors in
nine-dimensional space, and we would be
trying to find the combination that hit
the correct right-hand side B.
And we might also ask the question
can we always do it?
Can we get every right-hand side B? And
certainly, it will depend on those nine
columns.
Some Sometimes the answer will be yes.
If I picked a random matrix, it would be
yes, actually. If I used MATLAB and just
used the random command, picked out a 9
by 9 matrix
I guarantee it would be good. It would
be non-singular, it would be invertible,
all beautiful. But
if I choose those columns so that
they're not
independent
so that they're they're so that the the
ninth column is the same as the eighth
column
then it contributes nothing new, and
there would be right-hand sides B that I
couldn't get.
Can you sort of
think about
nine vectors in nine-dimensional space
and take their combinations? That's
really the
the central thought that that you get
kind of used to
in linear algebra. Even though you can't
really visualize it, you sort of think
you can after a while.
Those nine
columns and all their combinations may
very well fill out the whole
nine-dimensional space.
But if the ninth column happened to be
the same as the eighth column and gave
nothing new, then probably what it would
fill out would be
I hesitate even to say this. It would be
a com-
a sort of
plane
an eight-dimensional plane inside
nine-dimensional space.
And it's those eight-dimensional planes
inside nine-dimensional space that we
have to work with eventually.
For now, let's stay with the nice case
where
uh
the matrices work. We can get every
right-hand side B, and here we see how
to do it with columns.
Okay. There was one step that I real-
which I realized I was saying in words
that I now want to write in letters.
Because I'm coming back to the matrix
form of the equation
so let me write it here.
The matrix form of my equation of my of
my
system is some matrix A times some
vector X equals some right-hand side B.
Okay.
So, this is a multiplication, A times X,
matrix times vector, and I just want to
say, how do you multiply a matrix by a
vector?
Okay, so I'm just going to create a
a matrix.
Let me take
2 5 1 3
and let me take a vector
X to be, say, 1 and 2.
How do I multiply a matrix by a vector?
And
just We'll just think a little bit about
matrix notation and how to do that
multiplication. So, let me say how I
multiply a matrix by a vector.
Actually, there are two ways to do it.
Let me tell you my favorite way.
It's a It's It's columns again. It's a
column at a time. For me, that matrix
this matrix multiplication says I take
one of that column and two of that
column and add.
So, this is in my the way I would think
of it
is one of the first column
and two of the second column
and and let's just see what we get.
So, in the first
component, I'm getting a two and a 10,
I'm getting a 12 there. In the second
component, I'm getting a one and a six,
I'm getting a seven.
So, that
that matrix times that vector is 12 7.
Now
you could do that another way.
You could do it a row at a time.
You could do and you would get this 12,
and actually, I pretty much did it here.
This way, two I could take that row
times my vector. This is This is all the
time. This is the idea of a dot product.
This vector times this vector, 2 * 1 + 5
* 2 is the 12.
This vector times this vector, 1 * 1 + 3
* 2 is the 7.
So, I can do it by rows and in each row
each row times my X is what I'll later
call a dot product.
But I also like to see it by columns. I
see this as a linear combination of the
columns. So, here's my point. A times X
is a
combination
of the columns
of A.
That's
uh how I hope you will think of A times
X
when we need it. Right now, we've got
with small ones, we can always do it in
different ways, but later,
think of it that way.
Okay, so that's uh
um
the picture for uh 2 by 2 system
and if the right-hand side B happened to
be 12 7, then of course, the correct
solution would be 1 2.
Okay, so let me come back next time
to a systematic way using
elimination
to find the solution, if there is one
to any a system of any size
and find out
because the system because eliminate if
elimination fails
find out when there isn't a solution.
Okay, thanks.
Hey.